VINCENT J. SCHAEFER PAPERS (UA902.010) 1891-1993
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
- Atmospheric Sciences Research Center, 1950-1993; Undated; 6; 16.0
  The ASRC was designed in memory of the atmosphere that Schaefer enjoyed at the General Electric Research Laboratory in the 1930s and 1940s, where scientists were allowed plenty of freedom to conduct their experiments and Director Willis Whitney asked each day if his researchers were having fun. Besides conducting their own original research, ASRC scientists were always in contact with other professionals around the United States and internationally, sharing their research and collaborating on new ideas. The Center was also an ideal location for budding scientists from the University at Albany to collaborate with professionals. Schaefer brought some of the best scientists of the day to the ASRC thanks to his contacts from General Electric and Munitalp. Ray Falconer, Bernard Vonnegut, and Duncan Blanchard all became part of the ASRC family as it grew from the G.E. airplane hangar, to a building at 100 Fuller Road by the SUNY Albany uptown campus (1978), and finally to 251 Fuller Road (1997) where it is part of the Center for Environmental Sciences and Technology Management (CESTM).
  Although Schaefer was the principle founder of the ASRC, Dr. David Barry and Dr. Eugene McLaren were among the first directors while Schaefer was director of research (and chairman of the Scientific Advisory Committee.) However, Schaefer became overall director in 1965, a position he held until his retirement from the ASRC and teaching in 1976. Given the title of Professor Emeritus, he remained an advisor to the ASRC for years after.
  - Administrative Files, 1954-1990; Undated; 6.1
    The majority of the administrative files consist of correspondence; as director of research and then overall director of the ASRC, Schaefer was in constant contact with administrators of SUNY Albany, local colleagues, and other professionals in the field. There are also documents dealing with budget issues, grant applications, conferences, and operation of the N.S.I. field stations.
    - ASRC Staff Meetings, 1960-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - ASRC -SUNYA Advisory Committee-Photo and List, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - ASRC-SUNYA: Dissemination of Information, Ideas and Activities Related to Environmental Concern, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Australia-International Conference on Cloud Physics, 1961 September 11-1961 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Book of Project Guests and Participants (Assorted), 1964-1969 (Oversized 8)
    - Budget Forms, Supplies, Correspondence Relating to Nuclei Studies, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Budget, SUNYA- News Clipping and Memo, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - College for Environmental Studies: Preliminary Plans, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Committee for Business Operations, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Contracts and Salaries, 1964-1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence: Allied Resin Corporation, East Weymouth, Massachusetts, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence: American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence: American Geophysical Union, 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence: Archaeology, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Biology 199-Potential Changes, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence: Björnsson, Sveinbjörn (with photos), 1969 November (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence: Blanchard, Duncan, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence: Blanchard, Duncan-Report by Angie Barger (2 articles included), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence: Bollay, E., Operations of Offshore Airport Nuclear Reactor Facilities (Unpublished Typescript), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence: Breed, W.J. and Mackimon, D.J., Proposal to Four Corners Regional Commission to Build a Minimal Resources House in Flagstaff (Unpublished Typescript and letter), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence: Cheng, Roger-Acid Rain (with photos), ca. 1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence: Cloud Physics Committee American Meteorological Society, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence: Conservation Issues, 1954-1962 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence: Corning, Erastus 2nd, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence: Crudge, Vernon, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence: Crudge, Vernon-Lightning Strikes (with paper by V.P. Idone and R.W. Henderson), 1982 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence: Department of the Interior/Bureau of Reclamation-Weather Modification, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence: Dessens, Jean-Paper by T.L. Black (Paper Included), 1978 November; 1978 December (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence: Droessler, Earl G. Administrative Dean for Research North Carolina State University(with photo), 1967-1974 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence: Ebenezer Howard Project, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence: Electrostatics, 1972-1989 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence: Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence: Environmental Research Institute (Frank L. Craig-Head), 1968-1976 (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
    - Correspondence: Farrington Observatory-Sale, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence: Five Rivers Project, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence: Fostoria Corporation, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence: Fradkin (P)"Huge Power Plants Pose Threat", Akwesasne Notes 2.7, 1970 November; 1970 December (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence: Garstka, Walter U., 1962-1977 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence: General, 1955-1970 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence: General, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence: General, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence: General, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence: General, 1979-1992; Undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Correspondence: General Electric, 1968; 1973 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence: General Letterbook, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence: General Letterbook, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence: General Letterbook, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: General Letterbook, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - Correspondence: General Letterbook, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: General Letterbook, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: Gilleland, H., Museum of Northern Arizona Lake Powell (Correspondence, Notes and Maps), 1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: Grant, Lewis O.- Colorado State University, Pyrotechnic Tests, 1964 April 03; 1966 November 15 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence: Hailstone Studies, 1957-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence: Health Contracts, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence: Hebbs, Pater V., Project Cirrus, University of Washington, Seattle W.A, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence: Hennigan, Robert D., State University College of Forestry at Syracuse University, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence: Herrick, C.S., "Rolling Cylinder Heat Storage System" General Electric Research Laboratory, Schenectady, New York, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence: Heymsfield, G. (Unpublished Typescript), 1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence: Hogan, Austin, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence: Johnson, C.E., Superintendent, Glen Canyon National Park Service, Page, Arizona, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence: Kalliroscope, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence: Krick, Irving P.- Weather Modification, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
    - Correspondence: Lanford, O.E., Chancellors Panel on University Purposes, 1960-1981 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence: Magono, C., Department of Geophysics, University of Hokkaido, Sapparo, Japan, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence: Malkus, Joanne S.- With Articles, 1964; 1966 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence: Max C. Fleischmann Foundation, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence: Metropolis Exhibits, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence: Mitchell (H.A), Associate Provost for the Health Sciences, University of Missouri-Kansas City, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence: Moore, A.D. University of Michigan, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence: Moore, A.D. University of Michigan, 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence: Morris, Edward A., 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence: Morse, R.S.- Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence: Muir, A.J.- Sonic Development Corp., 1970 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence: Namias, Jerry-Letter and Symposium Booklet, 1986 August; 1987 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence: National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR), 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence: National Center for Atmospheric Research and Select Planning Group-"A Plan for a National Hail Field Experiment", 1969 February (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence: National Science Foundation-Grants, 1960; 1964 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence: Natural Sciences Institute, 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence: New York State Department of Transportation, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence: New York State Fruit Testing Cooperative Association, A Catholic of New and Noteworthy Fruits, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence: North American Weather Consultants/Eugene Bollay (Includes Research Paper), 1954 December 07; 1980 October 16 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence: Office of Natural Research Atmosphere Sciences Program "Monitoring the Air Pollution Over the Oceans" (Rough Draft), 1970 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence: Ottavio, Vittori, 1966-1974 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence: Pellett(G), NASA-Langley Research Center (Shuttle Environmental Impact Report), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence: Recommendations (VJS), 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence: Regional Haze Analysis, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence: River of the Sky Atmospheric Resources Film Script Copy #5 by W.L. Rusho, 1966 June (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence: Rose, Bruce M., 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence: Schaefer, James (Son), 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Correspondence: Schaefer (VJ), Reprints, 1955-1962 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence: Schley, R.A (Unpublished typescript), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence: Scientific American, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence: Smith-Johannsen, Robert, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence: South Dakota Weather Control Commission, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Correspondence: Stanley Newman Company, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence: State of New York Council of Environmental Advisers (Heller, Austin N.), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Correspondence: State University of New York Cloud Seeding, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence: Storm Conference, Springfield, MA, 1981 March 20-1981 March 22 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Correspondence: Sturges, Paul M., 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Correspondence: The Council of the City of Sydney, Australia, City Health Department, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Correspondence: The San Francisco Peaks, Arizona (VJS), 1972 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Correspondence: The Wing Company: Enthalex Energy Recovery Wheel, Undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Correspondence: United Aircraft Corporate Systems Center-ESSA Special Room Proposals (with supplementary materials), 1965 November 02; Undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Correspondence: Vause, E.H.- Charles F. Kettering Foundation, 1973 July 09 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Correspondence: Vonnegut, B. and I.K. Yang (with Article Reprints), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Correspondence: Wilson, S.C.- Includes Rolex Award Application, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Correspondence: Xerox Corporation-Duplication of Schaefer Research Photos, Images Included, 1976 May 06 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Drone and Vortices Field Observation Program, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Evaluation of the ASRC, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Field Research Seminar- Proposal to the National Science Foundation (Schaefer and D.G. Barry), 1962 April 15 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Five Rivers Institute, Development, Undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Geophysics Research Program Possibilities, Undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Grants, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Inventories of Reprints, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Joint Proposal of ASRC/ACR: Feasibility of Recycling Life Support Systems, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Mailing List: Final Report, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Maps/Charts/Plans for Space Needs at ASRC, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Memorandum on Meeting of Potential Users of Electron Microprobe, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Mohawk River Development Members of Sub-Committees, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Mohnen, Dr. Volker- Correspondence and Personnel Papers, 1970-1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Natural Scientists Institute: Potential Resources, 1975 November 13 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - NSI Candidates *Restricted*, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - NSI Candidates *Restricted*, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Planning Notes, Administrative and Research, 1982; 1986; Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Program on Science and Technology Studies, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Proposal Rating Sheets, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Schenectady Cloud Physics Facility- Memo, 1970 September 10 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Schenectady County Cloud Physics Laboratory- Potential Purchase, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Spain PEP Station, 1978 May 08 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Sponsored Research and Sponsored Programs, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Staff Meeting, 1980 December 09 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Student Leadership Programs (N.S.I), 1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Summer Staff, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - SUNYA Presidents Report- With Blurb on ASRC's Volker Mohnen (p.12), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - The Lewis Swyer Senior Fellowship, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Educational Activities, 1959-1992; Undated; 6.2
    Schaefer saw research opportunities via the ASRC that promised to have national and even international implications as environmental concerns became more public in the 1960s and 1970s. He was engaged frequently to speak about his research, both to other professionals and to “everyday” people who might be interested in learning more about issues like acid rain or solar energy. He also participated on committees and commissions who were given the responsibility of investigating scientific dilemmas of the day and presenting findings to the government. This subseries contains materials from those speaking engagements, trips, and committees.
    - Adventures Ahead, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - African Eclipse Cruise, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - African Eclipse Cruise, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 3-9)
    - Ambassador College Research Department, Hippies, Hipocrisy [sic] and Happiness, Pasadena, California, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - ASRC Scrapbook: Schenectady Tornado, 1960 June 24 (Oversized 8)
    - Basic Studies in Experimental Meteorology Field Locations and Research Projects, Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Capitaland Natural Science Center-Tivlo Lakes Nature Study Sanctuary- Schaefer Award with citation and brochure, Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Carnahan(R.L), NOAA Industrial Meteorology News Clips, 1970 October 13 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Caumsett State Park, Long Island (Brochure, Notes, Correspondence), 1973 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Chancellor's Fellows (MSS), Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Chautauqua- Type Short Courses for College Teachers, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Chautauqua- Type Short Courses for College Teachers, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Chautauqua- Type Short Courses for College Teachers (application forms, correspondence, teachers materials, rosters of participants, maps), 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
    - Chautauqua- Type Short Courses for College Teachers (application forms, schedules, timetables, grant forms), 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 21-23)
    - Chautauqua- Type Short Course Program, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Chautauqua- Type Short Courses for College, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Commission on Science Education, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 26-28)
    - Commission on Science Education, 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    - Cooperative College- School Science Program Guide for Preparation of Proposals, Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Cooperative United States of China Short Course Program for College and University Faculty Development Directory, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Dedicated Environmental Education for Posterity (DEEP), 1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Discovery Center of the Capital District (correspondence, proposal, mission statement), 1984 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Education: Leadership Programs, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Educational Monographs in the Atmospheric Sciences (American Meteorological Society), 1963-1965 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Environmental Education, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Environmental Studies #1, 1970 September (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Environmental Studies Program, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Environmental Studies Program, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Five Rivers Project: Outstanding Students, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Klinger Scientific Apparatus Corp., Experiments in Optics, Part 2, Bulletin 101-2, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Melander, Kathleen, Science Teacher (3rd & 4th grade letters and notebooks), 1954-1956 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Membership Cards, V.J. Schaefer, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Mercy College, Dobbs Ferry, New York- A 1967-1968 Conference Series: Teacher Preparation in the New Industrial State (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - National Science Foundation, 1964-1979 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - National Science Teachers (notebook), Undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Natural Sciences Institute, Fredonia, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Proposal for Reorientation, Undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Rochester Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1940-1967 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Schaefer Consulting, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
    - Schaefer Quiz to Graduate Students in the Atmospheric Sciences, Undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Schaefer V.J "A Formula for Happiness" (Notes used in giving commencement address at lake Pleasant Central School), Undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Schaefer V.J "A Program on Meteorological Research", Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (Typescript, photograph, memorandum), 1959 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Schaefer, V.J and Mohnen, V., Atmospheric Science, Test Edition, AAAS Study Guides on Contemporary Problems- Part of the Chautauqua-Type Short Courses for College Teachers Program, Study Guide, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Schaefer V.J and Mohnen V.A, "The Sciences, Motions and Sinks of Trace Gases and Fine Particles in the Global Ecosystem", Course for Academic Credit(Syllabus), 1972 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Schaefer V.J, Chautauqua Short Course Lectures for Environmental Planning (Unpublished Typescript), 1972 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Schaefer V.J, "Factors Which Led to The Foundation of ASRC Thirty Years Ago (unpublished Mss.), 1991 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Schaefer V.J Final Report of the Natural Sciences Institute, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Schaefer V.J "Meteorological Questions and Answers" prepared for the Hand of Wisdom game (typescript), Undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Schaefer V.J "Observation, Serendipity and Climatic Change, Journal of College Science Teaching 4.1 (pg. 19-22), 1974 September (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Schaefer V.J "Preliminary Draft of Proposal to National Science Foundation", Prepared by Vincent J. Schaefer for the radio Astronomy observatory, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (typescript), 1959 February (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Schaefer V.J, Salkever L.R, and Widmer W.R, Multidisciplinary Program for Secondary School Teachers, The Research Foundation of State University of New York and State University of New York at Albany, 1973 October 12 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Schaefer V.J, The Early Days of ASRC, Undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Science Research Associates, Inc., 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 40-41)
    - Science Teaching (guides, notices, programs), 1953-1974 (Box 5, Folder 42-44)
    - Scientific Adventures (photographs, issues, adventure kits), Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Senior Science Seminar, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Serendipity Hall, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Simon's Rock Early College, 1972-1977 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Report, New York, NY, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - State of New York Commission on Environmental Education, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - State of New York Temporary State Commission on Youth Education in Conservation, 1970-1973 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
    - SUNY- State Teachers College, Albany, New York Notebook, Undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Student Science Training Program (Pre-college) for High-Ability Secondary School Students, Undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Susquehanna Environmental Education association, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Talcott Mountain Science Center (brochures, plans, correspondence, reports, experiment possibilities), 1986 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Technical Glossary, Undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - The Experimental Earth Science Institute, Vestal, New York (correspondence), 1967 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Union College-G.E. Science Fellowship for Teachers, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - University of Michigan (correspondence), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Volunteers in Technical Assistance (VITA), 1978 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
    - Waterways '74 Project, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Whiteface Mountain Field Station Science Lectures Announcement, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - General Research, 1950-1993; Undated; 6.3
    Although Schaefer had administrative duties as director of research, as well as overall director of the ASRC in later years, he still made as much time as possible for conducting his own research. In addition to experiments carried out in New York’s Capital Region, he oversaw research at the Whiteface Mountain Field Station and Observatory as well as Flagstaff, Arizona, and led highly successful expeditions in the Yellowstone National Park. His fascination with particle studies continued during his ASRC years, leading to crucial investigations of carcinogens, acid rain, effects of particulate matter on global weather, aerosol studies, and much more. He also took great interest in alternative energy sources, solar energy specifically. Of course, cloud studies and ice-forming nuclei also remained a passion of Schaefer’s. This subseries mainly consists of Schaefer’s own investigations into those kinds of topics and offers a glimpse of his own notes, calculations, and observations on the subjects of interest to him.
    - Acid Rain, 1974-1984 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Aerosol Report, 1976-1977 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Aerosol Studies-Measurements and Notes, 1971-1976 (Box 8, Folder 3-6)
    - Aerosol Studies-Research Notebook, 1950-1971 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Air Pollution in the Household (Measurements, lists, pictures), 1971 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Air Pollution/Particle Studies, Undated (Box 8, Folder 9-10)
    - Air Pollution/Particle Studies, Part II: Gases, Sources, Motions, and Sinks, Undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - In the Adirondacks (Measurements, calculations and photos), 1974 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Air Quality in The Colorado Plateau Region (with notes and measurements), Undated (Box 8, Folder 13)